Guide to the Dorothy Gallagher Research Files on Carlo Tresca TAM.117
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Dorothy Gallagher Research Files on Carlo Tresca
1917-1988
TAM.117
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
1.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
Carlo Tresca (1897-1943), a charismatic Italian-born anarchist, labor agitator and newspaper editor, was one of the most fascinating figures of the American Left prior to World War II. Dorothy Gallagher, a New York City-based freelance writer is the author of All the Right Enemies: The Life and Murder of Carlo Tresca (Rutgers University Press, 1988). The collection consists of Gallagher’s subject files, interview notes and research notes created in preparation for publication of her book.
Gallagher, Dorothy
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
This collection of Carlo Tresca research files was donated to the Tamiment Library by Dorothy Gallagher in February 2004. The accession number associated with this gift is 2004.017.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Dorothy Gallagher (nee Rosenbloom), was born in Brooklyn to immigrant parents from Ukraine who were devoted members of the Communist Party. A New York-based writer, Gallagher began her career as features editor for Redbook magazine. She then became a freelance writer, publishing in The New York Times Magazine, The New York Times Book Review, and Grand Street. She is the author of three books: Hannah’s Daughters: Six Generations of an American Family, 1876-1976 (1976), All the Right Enemies: The Life and Murder of Carlo Tresca (1988), How I Came into My Inheritance: And Other True Stories (2001), and Strangers in the House: Life Stories (2006).
Often described as a “freelance revolutionary,” Carlo Tresca (1879-1943) was one of the most compelling and colorful figures of the American left prior to World War II. A newspaper editor, labor organizer, civil libertarian, anarchist, anti-Fascist and anti-Stalinist, Tresca had absorbed his fiery socialist principles and had been active as a trade-unionist and editor in his native Abruzzi before immigrating to the United States in 1904.
After joining the International Workers of the World (IWW) in 1912, Tresca was involved in a number of strikes, including the Lawrence, Massachusetts textile strike (1912), the New York City hotel workers' strike (1913), the Paterson silk strike (1913), and the Mesabi Range, Minnesota, miners’ strike (1916). He edited a newspaper called L’Avvenire (The Future), first in Pennsylvania and, from 1913, in New York City. Its successor, from 1917, was Il Martello (The Hammer). Tresca’s uncompromising anarcho-syndicalist views resulted in frequent clashes with local and federal authorities, and repeated confiscation of his publications.
He devoted considerable energy to campaigning on behalf of Sacco and Vanzetti in the 1920s and also became preoccupied with the struggle against fascism. Pursued by the U. S. government at the behest of the Mussolini regime, he survived several assassination attempts by fascist supporters. The Spanish Civil War intensified his anti-Communist activity and propaganda, earning him more enemies on the American left.
On the evening of January 11, 1943, Tresca was shot to death on the sidewalk in front of his office at Fifth Avenue and 15th Street. Over the years there has been a lively debate about which of Tresca’s many enemies might have been behind the murder. His murder was never prosecuted.
Sources:
Gallagher, Dorothy, All the Right Enemies: The Life and Murder of Carlo Tresca. New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers University Press, 1988.
Pernicone, Nunzio, Carlo Tresca: Portrait of a Rebel. New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2005.
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of the collection consists of Gallagher’s subject files on persons, institutions and events relating to Tresca. These files are largely composed of Gallagher’s handwritten notes, although some primary material, in particular newspaper clippings, is included. Items of interest include files on figures such as mobster Carmine Galante (believed by many to have murdered Tresca), labor organizer Elizabeth Gurley Flynn (romantically linked to Tresca), Italian-American Labor Council co-founder Vanni Montana, Italian model/actress/photographer Tina Modotti and American Communist Julia Stuart Poyntz, who disappeared in 1937.
In addition, the collection contains copies of files kept on Tresca by various governmental agencies. Most important of these are from the Casellario Politica Centrale, an agency under the aegis of the Italian Ministry of Internal Affairs and devoted to surveillance of anarchists, socialists and other subversives. Other notable files are portions of Tresca’s FBI file, as well as files from now-defunct U.S. government agencies, such as the Bureau of Narcotics, the Office of Strategic Services and the Office of War Information. Files from the U.S. Post Office document the suppression of circulation of Il Martello, Tresca’s Italian-language newspaper.
Gallagher’s handwritten notes from a number of her interviews are also included. Some are with significant figures in Tresca’s life and others with relatives of these persons, for example, Harrison De Silver (Margaret De Silver’s son), Jane Bobba (daughter of Elizabeth Gurley Flynn’s sister Bina Flynn, one of Tresca’s lovers), Peter Martin (the son of Bina Flynn and Carlo Tresca), and Len and Roma Giovannitti (children of Arturo Giovannitti).
The collection also contains copies of correspondence obtained by Gallagher from various archives and collections. Of special note are letters to and from Margaret De Silver, John Dos Passos, Herbert Solow, and Hannah Green, and correspondence between Harry Weinberger and Tresca, dating from 1938.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically.
Organized into 1 series:
1. Subject Files, 1917-1988.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Carlo Tresca: Dorothy Gallagher Research Files: Oral Histories (OH 085)
Carlo Tresca "Autobiography" (typescript) (TAM 443)
John Nicholas Beffel Papers (TAM 055)
Elizabeth Gurley Flynn Papers (TAM 118)
Elizabeth Gurley Flynn: Martin/Bobba Papers (TAM 348)
Elizabeth Gurley Flynn: Roz Baxandall and Helen Camp Research Files (TAM 224)
Casellario politico centrale.; DeSilver, Marguerite; Dos Passos, John, 1896-1970; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; Galante, Carmine.; Giovannitti, Arturo M., 1884-1959; Mafia.; Martin, Peter, 1923-; Modotti, Tina, 1896-1942; Montana, Vanni B., 1902-; Pernicone, Nunzio, 1940-; Poyntz, Julia Stuart, 1886-1937?; Solow, Herbert, 1903-1964; Tresca Memorial Committee, New York.; Tresca, Carlo, 1879-1943.; United States. Dept. of Justice.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation.; Anti-fascist movements |z Europe.; Antisemitism.; Case files.; Children |x Institutional care |z Europe |v Pictorial works.; Children |z Europe |v Portraits.; Correspondence.; Demonstrations |z Europe |v Pictorial works.; Employee rights.; Holocaust survivors |z Europe |v Portraits.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Interviews.; Jewish labor unions |z United States.; Jewish libraries |z Europe |v Pictorial works.; Jewish refugees |z Europe |v Portraits.; Jews |z Europe |v Portraits.; Labor leaders |z Europe.; Labor leaders |z United States |v Portraits.; New York (N.Y.); Race discrimination.; Refugee camps |z Europe |v Pictorial works.; Research notes.; Resistance movements, War |z Europe.; Socialists |z Europe.; Theater, Yiddish |z Germany |v Pictorial works.; World War, 1939-1945 |x Civilian relief |v Pictorial works.; World War, 1939-1945 |x Jews |x Rescue.
- Series 1: Subject Files, 1917-1988.
  - Bell, Daniel: Interview, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bobba, Jane: Interview, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bollato, John: Interview, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cape Cod and Martha’s Vineyard: CT’s Summer Visits, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Casellario Politico Centrale (CPC) Files (I), 1927-1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Casellario Politico Centrale (CPC) Files (II), 1927-1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Casellario Politico Centrale (CPC) Files (III), 1927-1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Coleman, Lester: Interview, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Communists: General Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - De Silver, Burnham: Interview, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - De Silver, Harrison: Interview, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - De Silver, Margaret: Correspondence (to Beatrice Tresca Canzanelli), 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Death of an Editor (CBS-TV Program), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dolgoff, Sam: Interview, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dos Passos, John: Correspondence (to Jack Diggins), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Farrell, James: Interview, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation Files: Antifascism, 1925-1926, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation Files: General, 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation Files: Murder Investigation, 1943-1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Federal Bureau of Narcotics, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley: Sabotage (IWW Pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Frager, Jack: Interview, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Galante, Carmine, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Genco, Joseph: Interview, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - General Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Genovese, Vito, 1946, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Gibson, Roland: Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Giovannitti, Len: Interview, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Green, Hannah: Correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Hamburger, Anna (Anna Walling): Interview, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Harkavy, Minna, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hayes, Eleanor Rice, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hunter, Mary, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Italian Vice Consulate Bombing (Scranton, PA), 1931, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Josephs, Peter Colt: Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Lipsky, Eleazar: Interview, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Luciano, Charles (Lucky), undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - L’Unita Operaia, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Mafia, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Manuscript: World War I and 1919 period, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Martin, Peter: Interview and Correspondence, 1979, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Marcantoni, Vito, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Il Martello: United States Post Office Files, 1917-1921 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Meteorological Reports (United States Department of Commerce), 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - The Militant, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Modotti, Tina, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Montana, Vanni, 1948, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Morroni, Furio: Synopsis of The Tresca Case, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Murder: General Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Murder and Funeral: Clippings, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Murder Investigation, 1943-1946 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - New York County District Attorney Files, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - New York Police Department, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Pernicone, Nunzio: “Carlo Tresca: A Brief Sketch” (from La Parola del Popolo, Nov/Dec 1978) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Pirani, Albert: Interview, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Popek, Dave: Interview, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Poyntz, Juliet Stuart, 1938, 1946, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Reiger, Roma (Roma Giovannitti): Interview, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Solomon, Sidney: Interview, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Solow, Herbert: Correspondence, 1945, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Tresca Memorial Committee, 1945-1950 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - United States Department of Justice Files, 1917-1943 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - United States Department of Labor: Immigration Files, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - United States Department of State Files, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - United States Military Intelligence Department, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - United States Naval Intelligence Department Files, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - United States Office of Strategic Services (OSS) Files, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - United States Office of War Information Files, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Wayne State University: Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Weinberger, Harry: Correspondence (with Carlo Tresca), 1938 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Weisbord, Vera: Interview, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Wolfe, Ella: Interview, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 58)